Finding Aid for Collegiate Institute for Values and Science (University of Michigan) records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Collegiate Institute for Values and Science (University of Michigan) records 1974-1990
University of Michigan. Collegiate Institute for Values and Science.
8.5 linear feet
87115 Bimu C560 2
Collected material relating to the debate over the University of Michigan's participation in genetic research, mainly recombinant DNA, and broader issues of ethics and values in scientific research.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers (Donor No. 7042 ) were donated in two accessions by Professor Nick Steneck. The third accession was part of a transfer of miscellaneous records from the Detroit Observatory (Donor No. 5123 ).
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open for research.
The Collegiate Institute for Values and Science (CIVS) was founded in the 1976/77 academic year for the purpose of facilitating discussions among scholars regarding scientific research and values. With the encouragement of Billy Frye, Dean of the College of Literature, Science and the Arts, and with funds earmarked for interdisciplinary programs, the Institute shaped into a monthly faculty seminar under the direction of faculty members Eric Rabkin, Nick Steneck, and Gordon Kane, with assistance from Roy (Skip) Rappaport.
CIVS initially concerned itself with the debate over research on recombinant DNA, which took place at the University of Michigan as well as on the national level, primarily during the years 1975-1978. The newly developed ability of scientists to manipulate the genetic code sparked sharp debates all across the nation, both within the scientific community and among non-scientists. As a major research institution the University of Michigan, along with Harvard and the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, was deeply involved with the controversy over DNA. The debate centered on three main issues. The first was the conflict between freedom of scientific inquiry and a more cautious approach to genetic research. In this context, the lessons derived from atomic fission and the development of nuclear weapons were recurring themes.
A second issue concerned the means of deciding whether or not to proceed with the research: cost-benefit analysis versus ethics. Some people argued that cost-benefit analysis was appropriate for immediate problems but was useless in determining the costs and benefits of long-range plans, such as DNA research.
Underlying the debate was a third issue: that of presumably ignorant public control as opposed to expert, scientific self-regulation. This issue is symptomatic of the ever-increasing gap in understanding between scientists and lay people. Again, both sides referred back to the development of atomic weapons: the public asserting its right to know what scientists were doing and to restrict or control their work, and the scientists insisting that they were the group best fitted to understand the ramifications of their work and to formulate the appropriate controls.
The specific fears aroused by DNA research were first, that the technology of genetic engineering might fall into the wrong hands, and second, that bacteria created in the laboratory might accidentally escape and cause massive epidemics. In general, the public voiced the first concern; and scientists, who were more familiar with the nature of the research, emphasized the second.
At the University of Michigan, the debate originated in 1975 with a request to the Regents to build three "moderate risk containment facilities" for DNA research. The discussion was largely carried on within three committees, "A," "B," and "C," although there was also a great deal of public discussion of the issue. Committee "A" operated under the assumption DNA research would continue, and it therefore concerned itself with the renovation of laboratories for this purpose. Its proposals were submitted to the National Institutes of Health (NIH) in hopes of receiving grant money.
Committee "B" represented a broad spectrum of university departments, with an emphasis on the humanities and social sciences. The purpose of the Committee was to deal with the social, ethical, and legal consequences of DNA research. The Committee took the position that some work was too hazardous to be continued at all, while other work was necessary for the solution of immediate problems which could not be solved by other methods. This work was to be carried out in accordance with the guidelines established by the NIH. Committee "B" recommended that another committee be formed to review the work being done and to decide, on the basis of the NIH guidelines, whether to authorize further research. This committee was to include at least one scientist not involved in DNA research, and a nonscientist.
In the spring of 1976, the Regents voted to approve the building of moderate-risk facilities. At the same time, they adopted some of the restrictions urged by Committee "B," notably the continuation of the existing Committee "C," or the Biological Research Review Committee. Committee "C" functioned as the "watchdog" proposed by Committee "B," by monitoring the research being done in the new laboratories.
At the national level, the primary issue was the development of legislation that would allow the research to continue while simultaneously protecting the public. Several people from the University of Michigan went to Washington to testify before the House Subcommittee on Science, Research and Technology.
Between the years 1978 and 1990, the CIVS expanded its scope from concentrating mainly on the recombinant DNA debate to considering a wide variety of issues relating to science, research, values, and education. It also acquired a more formal structure and function. Two directors, Eric Rabkin (1978-1982) and Nicholas Steneck (1982-1990), and an Executive Committee provided the leadership for the institute during the decade. Membership of the organization included Fellows and Associates. Respected scholars pursuing research and interested in discussing value issues raised by their disciplines were invited to become Fellows; other persons who desired to participate in CIVS activities were named Associates.
The Institute held monthly dinner meetings, frequently with guest speakers, to discuss value issues (particularly those that involved science) and also hosted conferences and colloquia. An additional emphasis on teaching led to the development of undergraduate and graduate ethics courses and the sponsorship of an Elder Hostel group. Funding from various university and non-university sources enabled the organization to award summer research grants to applicants and to support such values-related projects as the student-run magazine Consider. Parallel to these activities initiated by CIVS, the Director also assumed additional responsibilities, "usually in response to requests for the services of someone who can bridge the gap between the sciences and the humanities" (First Annual Report, page 4). Thus, the Institute became directly involved with related groups such as the Integrity of Scholarship Task Force and the Academic Freedom and Academic Responsibility project.
CIVS came to an end in 1990 when Steneck became Director of the Historical Center and administrative interests turned to other projects.
The records of the Collegiate Institute for Values and Science document the activities and programs of the institute and several campus issues involving ethics and scientific research, most notably the debate over research on Recombinant DNA in the 1970s. The records are organized into four series; Recombinant DNA Controversy, Topical File Audiotapes and Alan Price records.
Subjects:
Genetic engineering.; Recombinant DNA--Research.; University of Michigan--Research.; Values--Study and teaching.; Science--Social aspects.; Steneck, Nicholas H.
Genre Terms:
Sound recordings.
- Recombinant DNA Research Controversy 1975-1980
  The Recombinant DNA Controversy series was received as part of the 1984 Accession. The series documents the years 1974-1982, with the bulk of the records centering on the years 1976-1978. Almost none of the material was created by the CIVS but was gathered from a variety of sources to document the Recombinant DNA Controversy and it impact the campus and community. Some of the material consists of photocopies of documents that may be found in other university record groups. The series has been divides into two subseries: Committees and Collected Materials.
  - Committees
    The Committees subseries includes the correspondence, minutes, recommendations and reports of Committees "A," "B," and "C," as well as some material from the Committee on the Feasibility of a P4 Facility for the CIC. ("P4" refers to the level of risk entailed in any given research.)
    - Committee "A," 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    - Committee "B"
      - Correspondence
        - 1975 (Box 1)
        - January-February 1976 (Box 1)
        - March 1976-January 1977 (Box 1)
      - Minutes
        - 1975 (Box 1)
        - 1976 (Box 1)
      - Recommendations 1976 (Box 1)
      - Report
        - Draft and Notes January-February 1976 (Box 1)
        - Final Report March 1976 (Box 1)
        - Critique of Report April 1976 (Box 1)
        - Response to Critique of Report April 1976 (Box 1)
      - Miscellanea (Box 1)
    - Committee "C" (Biological Review Committee)
      - Annual Reports 1977-1979 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence
        - 197-1976 (Box 1)
        - January-May 1977 (Box 1)
        - June-December 1977 (Box 1)
        - January-August 1978 (Box 1)
        - September-December 1978 (Box 1)
        - January-May 1979 (Box 1)
        - June-December 1979 (Box 1)
        - 1980 (Box 1)
      - Members and Function of Committee (Box 1)
      - Minutes 1976-1980 (Box 1)
      - Notes (Box 1)
      - Miscellanea (Box 1)
    - Committee on Industrial Cooperation 1977 (CIC) (Box 1)
    - Committee on the Feasibility of a P4 Facility for the Committee on Industrial Cooperation 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Collected Materials
    The Collected Works subseries includes correspondence, testimony and statements presented to the committees or at public forums, journal and magazine articles, newspaper clippings, records of congressional hearings on the topic of recombinant DNA, correspondence and statements of the regents and other university officials on the topic, and files collected by several individuals prominent in the discussion including Carl Cohen.
    Among the significant files are statements issued by the Ann Arbor City Council and the Ann Arbor Ecology Center; Correspondence, 1974-1982; and environmental impact statement; and files relating to a forum on DNA containing material relating to a public discussion of DNA research held at the University of Michigan in 1976.
    Individual files of Carl Cohen Helling, Robert Skolimowski, Henryk and Wright, Susan contain not simply material collected by these people, but also statements and notes by them which did not fit comfortably into other files.
    Files of the National Institute of Health (NIH), the. agency set guidelines for DNA research, contains the guidelines from 1976-1978, material from the NIH's Recombinant DNA Molecule Program Advisory Committee, and a folder of miscellanea.
    Articles and publications includes material from the poplar and scientific press. Included among them are several articles written by Carl Cohen, and a chapter entitled "The Discussion of Recombinant DNA at the University of Michigan" by Alvin Zander for a book edited by Steven Stich and David Jackson called The Recombinant DNA Debate (1976).
    Files relating to the Regents of the University of Michigan include correspondence, Sarah Power, Thomas Roach (both of whom were Regents at this time), Statements (made to the Regents) and Miscellanea.
    The United States Congress file consists mostly of material from the Subcommittee on Science, Research and Technology of the House Committee on Science and Technology. The file is divided into "Hearings/Testimony" and "Legislation."
    A file title, Miscellanea. includes interesting documents which, for lack of a better category, are located here. These include a paper discussing University Policies and Biological Hazards, and the architects' proposed plan for renovating existing laboratories.
    Unlike other controversies over the role of the University with regard to research, the papers in this collection do not suggest widespread student participation in the DNA debate. Nevertheless, several possible themes for historical research exist. Among these are the relations and tensions between the university and the larger society, between the sciences and humanities, between freedom of inquiry and limitations, and between the "experts" and the people. Reading the statements by various scientists and nonscientists may shed some light on the question of how the scientific community sets its agenda, and the larger issue of for whom and for what science is intended.
    - Ann Arbor City Council 1976 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Ecology Center 1976-1978 (Box 1)
    - Collected Materials
      - Individual files
        - Cohen, Carl (Box 1)
        - Helling, Robert (Box 1)
        - Skolimowski, Henryk (Box 1)
        - Wright, Susan (Box 1)
      - Journal/Magazine articles, 6 folders (Box 2)
      - Newspapers 1975-1980
        - Ann Arbor, 3 folders (Box 2)
        - Non-local, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Miscellanea, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Correspondence
      - 1974-1975 (Box 2)
      - 1976 (Box 2)
      - 1977 (Box 2)
      - 1978-1979 (Box 2)
      - 1980-1982 (Box 2)
    - Environmental Impact (Box 2)
    - Forum on DNA 1976-1977 (Box 2)
    - National Institute of Health (NIH)
      - Guidelines 1976-1978 (Box 2)
      - Recombinant DNA Molecule Program Advisory Committee (Box 2)
      - Miscellanea (Box 2)
    - News Releases 1976-1978 (Box 2)
    - Publications
      - Articles, by Carl Cohen (Box 2)
      - "The Discussion of Recombinant DNA at the University of Michigan," by Alvin Zander (Chapter for The Recombinant DNA Debate, Steven Stich and David Jackson, eds., 1977) (Box 2)
    - Regents of the University of Michigan
      - Correspondence 1976, 1980 (Box 2)
      - Power, Sarah Goddard 1975-1976, 1980 (Box 3)
      - Roach, Thomas (one folder and one notebook of documents relating to DNA debate) (Box 3)
      - Statements to the Regents 1975-1976 (Box 3)
      - Miscellanea (Box 3)
    - United State Congress
      (primarily Subcommittee on Science, Research, and Technology of the House Committee on Science and Technology)
      - Hearings/Testimony
        - 1976 (Box 3)
        - 1977, 3 folders (Box 3)
        - 1978 (Box 3)
      - Legislation 1978 (Box 3)
    - Miscellanea (Box 3)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files are arranged alphabetically, following the original order of the record group. Except where noted, correspondence files are organized chronologically. The series documents the Institute's administrative history, activities, research, and interactions with related organizations.
  - Academic Freedom and Academic Responsibility project 1983-1987
    - Articles (Box 4)
    - Committee membership lists (Box 4)
    - Correspondence (Box 4)
    - Fundraising (Box 4)
    - National Advisory Committee correspondence (Box 4)
    - Proposals and reports (Box 4)
  - Ad Hoc Classified Research Committee 1985 (Box 4)
  - Annual reports and summaries 1980-1986 (Box 4)
  - Charles Babbage Institute 1979-1980 (Box 4)
  - Colloquium 1980-1981, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Colloquium speakers 1981 (includes photographs) (Box 4)
  - Committee on Ethics, Humanism and Medicine 1979-1987, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Conference on Teaching of Ethics and Values in the University (later, Council on Ethics and Values in the University)
    - Conferences 1986-1987 (Box 4)
    - Conferences 1988-1989 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence 1985-1990 (Box 4)
    - Minutes 1987-1990 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (including summary reports) 1987-1990 (Box 4)
  - Consider magazine,1983-1986 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence 1983-1987 (organized alphabetically) (Box 4)
  - Course proposals
    - The World We Make 1979-1981 (Box 4)
    - 1986, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Elderhostel 1984-1986 (Box 4)
  - Ethics and Values Studies (of the National Science Foundation) 1985-1986 (Box 4)
  - Ethics Courses on the University of Michigan Campus 1986 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee
    - Correspondence 1979-1988 (Box 5)
    - Meetings 1983-1985 (Box 5)
    - Members
      - Chamberlain, John,1980-1986 (Box 5)
      - Gordon, Jesse 1979-1981 (Box 5)
      - Kane, Gordon
        - 1983 meeting presentation (Box 5)
        - Correspondence,1977-1984 (Box 5)
      - Rabkin, Eric
        - Correspondence,1978-1983 (Box 5)
        - Curriculum Vita 1982 (Box 5)
      - Steneck, Nick
        - Correspondence,1977-1987 (Box 5)
        - Miscellaneous 1978, 1982 (Box 5)
        - Reports, proposals, and testimony 1983-1987 (Box 5)
  - Health and Human Values Search Committee 1980-1981 (Box 5)
  - Integrity of Scholarship 1983-1987
    - Articles and reports (Box 5)
    - Cases (grievances alleging misconduct in research) 1983
    - Task Force Committee (Box 5)
    - Follow-up (Box 5)
  - Junto Conference 1983 (Box 5)
  - Library,1979-1984 (Box 5)
  - Medical Scientist Training Program 1985-1986 (Box 5)
  - Meetings and speakers 1980-1988 (Box 5)
  - Membership (including interest surveys) 1978-1986 (Box 5)
  - Microwave Project 1978-1980 (Box 5)
  - Newsletter 1987 (Box 5)
  - Nuclear Study 1979 (Box 5)
  - Other programs (research and ethics organizations at other institutions) 1979-1987, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Phoenix Memorial Project 1981-1987 (Box 5)
  - Related groups on the University of Michigan campus 1982-1987 (Box 5)
  - Staff position (potential) 1985 (Box 5)
  - Summer funding (applications for grants from CIVS)
    - 1979 (Box 5)
    - 1980 (Box 5)
    - 1981 (Box 5)
- Audio cassettes
  The Audio Cassettes series consists primarily of recordings from the 1983 International Student Pugwash Conference on Science, Technology, and Global Responsibility, which CIVS and especially Steneck helped to sponsor. As few paper records relating to this conference exist here, this subseries of 20 cassettes provides useful and interesting information about these science and values issues. The series also includes recordings from the Conference on Teaching of Ethics and Values in the University and other miscellaneous presentations.
  Researchers particularly interested in the history and administrative structure of the Institute itself should begin by looking at the 1986 First Annual Report in the "Annual reports and summaries" file, which provides a concise history of the organization as well as a summary of the year's activities and an evaluation of those activities. The "Executive Committee" subseries and the "Correspondence" and "Members" files also provide much information about the Institute itself.
  Researchers more interested in the values issues that the Institute explores might begin with the "Colloquium" and "Meetings and Speakers" files, which contain copies of speakers' presentations. Since documents relating to issues of science and values comprise the bulk of the accession, browsing through the various files will probably be most useful to researchers interested in those topics. The audio cassette series also contains detailed explorations of values issues.
  - International Student Pugwash Conference on Science, Technology, and Global Responsibility 1983 (arranged numerically)
    - 1-Nicholas Steneck, Billy Frye, Martin Kaplan, Michael Berger, David Hawkins (Box 6)
    - 2-David Hawkins ("QTA") (Box 6)
    - 3-Plenary II (Box 6)
    - 4-Plenary II (cont.) and III (Box 6)
    - 5-Plenary III (cont.) (Box 6)
    - 6-Plenary III (cont.) (Box 6)
    - 7-Plenary IV (Box 6)
    - 8-Plenary IV (cont.) (Box 6)
    - 9-Plenary IV (cont.) (Box 6)
    - 10-Michigan League (Box 6)
    - 11-15-Plenary V (Box 6)
    - 16-18-Plenary VI (Box 6)
    - 19-20-Working Group Reports
      - 19-Computers, Biotechnology and Resources; and Resources, Managing Technology and Security (Box 6)
      - 20-Group Reports (cont.): Security; Fred (Box 6)
  - Conference on Teaching of Ethics and Values
    (See folders in Topical series for schedules of these conferences.)
    - John H. D'Arms and Robert McAfee Brown March 7, 1987
      - Tape 1 (Box 6)
      - Tape 2 (Box 6)
      - Tape 3 (Box 6)
      - Tape 4 (Box 6)
    - Jon Brademas ("New York Vice President") 1988 (Box 6)
    - January 30, 1988 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous cassettes
    - Tom Dunn, "Realities and Limits of Progress," March 30, 1982 (Box 6)
    - Collegiate Institute (Box 6)
      (1 of 3"; other 2 missing)
    - L. Sklar, "Current Issues in the Philosophy of Science," March 9, 1983 (Box 6)
    - Robin Jacoby ("AF") (Box 6)
    - Interview with William Randolf Taylor, Professor Emeritus of Botany, regarding camera requisitioned in 1945 June 13, 1986
- Alan Price Records
  The final series consists of the records of Dr. Alan R. Price. These records include some material from Alvin Zander who chaired one of the policy committees before turning his files over to Price. Price had been involved in research at many levels while at the University of Michigan. In 1979 he was appointed Assistant Dean for Research and Development in the Medical School and directed the Office of Biomedical Research. In the early 1980s he became an administrator in the Office of the Vice President for Research (OVPR) and at one point served as the Interim Vice President for Research for the University. Price also served on the Research Policy Committee in the 1980s, and took a great interest in local and national events dealing with confidential military research at universities.
  The Alan Price Records series relates to publicity and policy debates concerning university research activities from 1981 through 1987. The materials primarily document debate over U.S. Department of Defense (DOD) grants that supported confidential weapons research at the university. These records are a valuable resource for those interested in the social unrest and peace movements on campus in the mid-1980s. The Research Policy Committee subseries and the Classified Research Policy Review subseries document research policy formation regarding the sensitive topic of weapons and defense particularly well. The papers are arranged by subject, with the following subseries: Animal Research, Classified Research Policy Review, Nuclear Free Zone, Peace Studies, Research News and Information, Research Policy Committee, Strategic Defense Initiative ("Star Wars"), University Research Initiative, and University Research Instrumentation Program. There is some topical overlap among the series which probably relates to Dr. Price's changing filing determinations over time.
  - Animal Research
    The Animal Research subseries consists of .1 linear feet of materials related to two committees concerning the care and use of laboratory animals at the University in the early 1970s and early 1980s. Records consist primarily of meeting minutes, correspondence, and reports.
    - Ad Hoc Committee to Review the Unit for Laboratory Animal Medicine (1973) (Box 7)
    - Committee on the Care and Use of Animals 1981-1984, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Classified Research Policy Review